You're not taking a photo?
怎麼不拍了？
I'm waiting for the cloud to move.
我在等雲離開
I see.
是喔，哪一朵雲？
That one.
那朵
Don't you get tired?
真虧你都拍不膩
It's just the sky.
不都一樣是天空嗎？
I think about
我總會想
what sort of face the sky is making today.
天空今天不知道長什麼樣子
I didn't know the sky had a face.
天空有臉嗎？
If that's what you mean, I understand too.
如果是這意思，我多少也能夠明白
TAIYAKI
（小田屋鯛魚燒）
What? Sora said that?
什麼 小空這麼說嗎？
She wants to meet Fuga Ichinose.
她說想見見一之瀨風雅
What for?
見面要做什麼？
To punch him in the face!
她要去賞他一拳
I think. I'm not sure.
之類的吧
Why did you join, Kenta?
你少插花了，你煩惱什麼啊？
We don't know where he is, though.
但我也不知道他人在哪
Hello!
大家好
-Hello. -Hi.
-嗨 -你好
Doctor Wataru, what's that you're holding?
涉師傅，你手上拿的是什麼？
Driftwood, from Ouse Island.
漂流木，逢瀨島的禮物
You got driftwood from a mysterious man?
跟神秘大叔買的漂流木嗎？
Yes.
是的
I just got sucked in and before I realized,
它感覺有種會把人吸進去的魔力
I had bought one.
忍不住就買了
I thought it'd match Odaya's Japanese style.
總覺得很適合小田屋的和風氣氛
-Here's your order. -You got this at Ouse Island, huh?
-您的餐點 -在逢瀨島買的啊？
You do scuba diving, right?
我記得你喜歡玩水肺潛水吧？
Yes.
是的
I wanted to forget about the real world.
我想暫時忘記現世
The real world?
現世？
Well,
沒什麼啦
this is awkward to say here,
在這裡說很不好意思
but lately Sora doesn't seem to be interested in me.
最近小空好像對我沒什麼興趣
Huh?
咦？
What's wrong?
怎麼一陣沉默？
Oh, no, it's just Sora's going through a lot right now.
不是，她最近有點事情
You haven't heard
難道說
anything from Sora, Doctor Wataru?
小空都沒告訴你嗎？
Nothing.
沒有
Maybe she doesn't want to tell me.
她可能不想跟我說吧
It's not like that.
不是這樣的
It's just, you know.
畢竟那件事
It's not something you can openly share with others.
不太好到處宣揚
Well, that makes me a bit sad.
但我覺得很寂寞
Because I did think I was her boyfriend.
我以為我應該算是她的男友
That was lame.
好丟臉
I'm very lame right now.
我真是太遜了
Men get pathetic and clingy like this so easily.
男人都是這樣 逐漸變得沒出息又不乾脆的吧
Well, not all men.
不是大家，應該只有我這樣吧
Wait! What about the girl you made the promise with
對了，那個
Huh? Did I misread the room?
我太白目了嗎？
I got my taiyaki to go, so I'll be on my way.
鯛魚燒已經都好了，我先告辭了
My clients are waiting too.
我下午還有客人
Oh, really?
這樣啊
Oh, no worries. From what I heard, it's a priceless piece.
不會，沒多少錢
But I did get ripped off.
雖然被坑了
I'm glad you like it.
幸好你們喜歡，我先走了
Thank you, come again.
謝謝你
Shunichiro. Why did you say that?
俊一郎，你幹嘛那樣說？
Because it's obvious that Sora should be
因為小空是配阿光啊
with Hikaru, right?
任誰來看都很明顯吧？
Sora has very little experience with romance,
不，小空沒什麼戀愛經驗
so she may not know
她可能沒有察覺到自己的對象是阿光
During dark times, whose hand do you want to hold on to?
在顛簸的黑暗道路上 想要捉住誰的手
Who do you want to lean on?
想緊緊依靠著誰
She might not know that
這就是戀愛
It's more likely that she thinks love is the man you'd want to
在燦爛晴朗的夏威夷海邊 想跟誰一起跳進水裡
go to the beach with in Hawaii on a bright and sunny day.
她大概以為這才是戀愛
Would she ever go to the beach in Hawaii with a man?
她有那種跟男人一起去 夏威夷海邊的機會嗎？
That wasn't the point.
你搞錯重點了
And this driftwood!
不過漂流木啊
I didn't know people sold these for a living.
原來有人靠賣這個討生活呢
Did something happen?
你遇到什麼煩惱嗎？
You don't have to talk about it.
不想說的話可以不用說
Because you're my boyfriend, Doctor Wataru.
因為你是我的男朋友啊
Mom isn't my birth mom.
我媽並非我的生母
She's just the person who raised me.
只是我的養母
-What? -My birth mother died.
什麼？
And I have a Dad who lives very far away, who I've never met.
我的爸爸不知人在何方，從未見過面
I shouldn't call him Dad.
我不想叫他爸爸
I have a birth father who abandoned my birth mother
那個拋棄我的養母，拋棄我生母的人
and the mother who raised me.
是我實質上的父親
You didn't know this until now?
你之前都不知道嗎？
I found out by chance.
完全不曉得，是突然之間發現的
I was overwhelmed by that,
因為心裡充滿各種情緒
so if I was ever cold to you…
我可能對你很冷淡
-I'm sorry! -It's fine.
-對不起 -不會
Were you able to talk with anyone?
你還好嗎？有跟誰商量這件事嗎？
My classmate, Irino.
我同學入野
I see.
是嗎？
We were drawing manga together. So it was by chance.
該怎麼說？
I don't think so.
我想應該不是碰巧吧
What?
什麼？
I wish I could've done something to help.
我當時若能幫上忙就好了
Anything.
如果我能幫你分擔的話
I'm sorry.
對…不起…
But it's not like that with Irino.
不過涉師傅，我跟入野不是那種關係
He's just a friend. We're not in love or anything.
只是朋友而已，沒有任何戀愛情愫
Really?
是這樣嗎？
Yes!
是的
And Irino has a supermodel girlfriend.
而且入野有個像模特兒一樣的女友
A girl with high hips.
腰線位置很高，我記得名字叫做心
Plus, he says weird things like he only likes girls that are
他還說他只愛比自己高的女人
taller than him.
真是莫名其妙
I see.
這樣啊
Anyways,
別說他了
I want to meet my father.
我想要去見我父親
That's how I feel.
有點想見他
The father who abandoned my birth mother and foster mother.
他拋棄扶養我與生下我的母親
He's evil, right?
簡直是大壞蛋
I want to punch him.
我要去賞他一拳
This is a photo of my father when he was young.
這是我父親年輕時的照片
What! Can I take a closer look?
什麼？借我看一下
Sure.
好的
Huh? What?
什麼？
-There are no clues or anything. -No.
-那上面沒有暗號喔 -不是的
"Fuga Ichinose."
一之瀨風雅
I don't want to Google him. It feels like I lost.
我不想自己查，有種先認輸的感覺
That makes no sense. Oh, I found him!
您在說什麼啊？查到了
Forever with You. It sounds familiar.
《永遠與你同在》…好像有聽過
It was a really popular show back in the day.
是以前超火紅的電視劇
Fuga Ichinose got his big break from this.
他就是因為這部戲大紅
I know this! My mother watched this show.
我知道，我媽是忠實觀眾
Are you rubbing how young you are in my face?
幹嘛趁機炫耀啊？年輕了不起喔？
But he hasn't been in anything else after that.
但他後來就沒有再出現了
Yes. He disappeared at the peak of his stardom.
沒錯，他不知為何在巔峰時期消失了
He retired, maybe?
引退嗎？
No one knows what he's doing now, right?
不知道他現在過得怎麼樣
I guess so…
應該
No, I'm sure.
肯定…是他
What?
什麼？
He's changed a lot, but he's the man collecting driftwood at Ouse Island.
雖然變了很多
-Driftwood? -Yeah.
-漂…漂流木？ -嗯
-You found him?
-找到人了？
Doctor Wataru found him collecting driftwood at Ouse Island.
涉師傅發現他在逢瀨島撿漂流木
Sorry, that doesn't make sense to me.
等等，我聽不太懂
But either way, so you found Fuga Ichinose?
總之就是找到一之瀨風雅了
That was his stage name, so it's not his real name.
那是藝名，不是他的本名
Right. Makes sense.
我想也是
You're gonna go see him?
你要去見他嗎？
I found him, so we're going.
既然都找到了，當然要去
I was calling you while packing.
我現在也正在整理行李
You're treating me so carelessly!
哇，好隨便，你對待我好隨便
What?
什麼？
The guy who sold this driftwood is Fuga Ichinose?
硬賣漂流木給涉師傅的人 就是一之瀨風雅？
He always did have a shady side, even back then.
他以前就有點奸詐的感覺
So…
所以
We're going to go see him.
我們決定去見他
Seriously?
真的假的？
Sora is determined.
小空講不聽啊
Apparently, Doctor Wataru got a little jealous.
涉師傅好像吃醋了
What?
什麼？
Because I talked about all this with you
因為我有跟你說這件事，卻沒告訴他
I see.
這樣啊
But it's not like that at all!
他真是誤會大了
Right.
是啊
You have a supermodel girlfriend with high hips. Kokoro, right?
況且你還有個腰線很高的 模特兒型女友呢
Sure do! We're all over each other!
對啊，我今天也跟她大放閃喔
I don't even think of you as a sister.
你對我來說就像妹妹一樣啦
But you know, Irino?
不過入野
Having a boyfriend
像這樣所謂的男友？戀人？
means someone gets jealous about you!
或者說男朋友的關係 對方就會像這樣吃醋呢
I said something to him like, "Sorry I was so cold."
我還說什麼“抱歉對你這麼冷淡”
You're an otaku too.
你自己也是宅男啊
So is it okay if we wait a bit until our next manga meeting?
總之我們的漫畫會議 可以過一段時間再說嗎？
Sure. But first, Fuga Ichinose, right?
當然，先處理一之瀨風雅吧
Yeah!
好
-Thank you. -Thank you!
-謝謝您
It's a good thing that Doctor Wataru asked him where he lives.
多虧涉師傅幫我們問到住處
Apparently, it's not exactly where he lives.
那好像不是他的家
What do you mean?
咦？什麼意思？
He doesn't have an address. He's always on the move.
他居無定所，似乎是到處流浪
Anyways, I got information on the residential area of the island.
我已經問到島上的住宅區位置了
Residential area?
住宅區？
They went to see him, huh?
她去見他啦？
Huh?
嗯？
She went to see her former lover, huh?
她去見以前的男人啦
Why are you saying it like that?
幹嘛故意這樣說？
Here?
這裡嗎？
Ring the doorbell.
門鈴呢？
-Are you joking? -What?
-你傻了嗎？ -什麼？
What, me?
我嗎？
You said you wanted to see him.
是你說要見他的
Wait.
等一下
Is my face okay?
媽媽的妝還好嗎？
Your makeup is pilling.
妝花掉了
I'll be back!
我去補妝
Can I help you?
你來我家有什麼事嗎？
Ichinose!
一之瀨先生！
Long time no see.
好久不見
It's me, Aoi.
我是小碧
Aoi Minase.
水無瀨碧
Do you not remember me?
難道你不記得我了嗎？
I'm sorry. Excuse me.
抱歉，失陪一下
Mom! Are you okay?
媽媽…你沒事吧？
"Mom"?
媽媽？
Are you mother and daughter?
你們是母女嗎？
Yes.
沒錯
And you came to talk to me about something?
你們來找我有什麼事嗎？
Did you come from Tokyo?
從東京來的嗎？
Yes.
是的
Would you like to come in?
不嫌棄的話，要進來坐嗎？
Here you are.
請喝
It's good!
好好喝
It's tea, made from angelica keiskei I got from the mountain.
這是我用後山採的明日葉泡的茶
I…
我…
I'm going to go explore outside.
出去探險一下
I was in love with you for a week.
我愛了你一個星期
I was still 23.
當時我只有23歲
I had just become an adult.
才剛成人沒多久
One week…
一星期
It may have been a forgettable week for you.
即便對你而言 只是轉眼就忘的一星期
But for me,
對我來說
it was a week
直到現在
that is still vivid in my memory.
仍是清楚刻在記憶中的一星期
After a week,
你在那一週後
you disappeared like a ghost.
就像神隱了一樣
I looked for you.
於是我到處找你
And then,
後來
I met Suzu.
便遇到了鈴小姐
I was just
我也許只是 你過去眾多女人的其中一位
But Suzu…
但是，鈴小姐
You remember Suzu Hoshino, right?
你還記得星野鈴小姐吧？
Suzu Hoshino…?
星野鈴
What?
什麼？
You don't even remember her?
你連她都不記得嗎？
-Ma? -"Ma"?
-真假？
It means "Are you serious?" It's a Gen Z term my daughter uses.
意思是“真的假的” 我女兒常常這麼說
It's rubbed off on me.
我被她影響了
You really don't remember Suzu Hoshino?
星野鈴小姐，你真的不記得她嗎？
She was an actress, in the same theater troupe as you.
是跟你同一個劇團的女演員
Yes.
喔
I remember someone like that.
好像有過這個人
After all,
畢竟已經是20年前的事了
when I was acting or in theater troupes.
還在劇團之類的演戲的時候…
Suzu passed away.
鈴小姐過世了
That girl is Suzu's…
一之瀨先生，那孩子是鈴小姐的…
She is your daughter. Her name is Sora.
也是你的女兒，她叫小空
Suzu
鈴小姐
passed away from a heart disease soon after giving birth to her.
生下她不久後就因心臟病過世了
I took her in
後來是我收養她
and raised her.
並養育她
You did?
你嗎？
Yes.
是的
I'm sorry for
我都不記得了
not remembering.
真的很抱歉
It's fine.
沒關係
Excuse me.
對了
I know this is weird to ask,
那個，很抱歉在這時候說這件事
but I'm a writer, and I have a deadline today.
其實我是個作家，今天是截稿日
Can I do a bit of work here?
我可以在這裡工作一下嗎？
Sure.
當然
Go ahead.
請便
Are you okay?
還好嗎？
Did you find something?
你看到什麼了嗎？
A striped shore crab.
是粗腿厚紋蟹
Here's a good one.
這個不錯
I will clean this.
我要把它清乾淨
The weak areas are decaying, so it peels right off.
脆弱的部分因為腐朽了 馬上就會被沖掉
Driftwood with a sturdy center is a good one.
好的漂流木只會留下堅硬的木心
Isn't it…
你在這種地方
Isn't it lonely living alone in a place like this?
你一個人住在這種地方不會寂寞嗎？
It is lonely.
很寂寞喔
How many years?
幾年？
How many years does it take
要花幾年
for a sturdy center to form?
才能留下堅硬的木心？
I'm not sure. Two or three years?
我不確定，兩三年吧
Or maybe more.
也許更久
Through nature's force,
在大自然的力量下
it can bump into rocks,
撞擊岩石
or be swallowed by waves,
隨波逐流
and be beaten against the shore.
被沖上海岸
The more time passes,
經過愈長的時間
the stronger the driftwood gets.
漂流木就愈強韌
It gets stronger the more it travels.
在旅程的途中，逐漸變得強壯
You can only get strong
沒有歷經撞擊
by bumping into rocks and getting
互相碰撞
beaten against the shore.
就不會變強壯
I want to try.
我想試試看
Go ahead.
請用
Ms. Aoi, are you listening?
小碧老師，您有在聽嗎？
Ms. Aoi?
-小碧老師？ -是
Sorry.
抱歉…
The manuscript is due at four today.
今天四點前要交稿
Yes. I'll send it over by then.
好的，我會確實完成工作
I'm sorry, at a time like this.
抱歉，在這種時候
Not at all.
不會
The series for Midsummer Skies are Dreams is starting soon.
《仲夏藍天之夢》才剛開始連載
I have to push through.
得好好加油
I want to start with something like, "The salamander was sad."
我想寫出像是 《山椒魚很傷心》的開頭
What do you mean?
什麼意思？
It's Masuji Ibuse. You don't know?
井伏鱒二，你不知道嗎？
Of course I know him, but…
我當然知道他
I want to start with a powerful first sentence.
我想用充滿魄力的一句話來開頭
I see. I'm sure Masuji Ibuse also thought, "Score!"
原來如此
I'm sure he did.
肯定是呀
And how is it going over there?
話說回來，那邊情況如何？
It's not going anywhere.
還能怎樣？
Fuga Ichinose forgot about me.
他根本把我忘了
-No way! -Yes, way.
-不會吧？ -是真的
And he pretended to forget about Suzu, too.
而且他還想假裝不記得鈴小姐
What I thought was one week of fateful love
我視為命中注定的那一星期
was only an ordinary week for him.
對他來說只是平凡無奇的一星期
Monday to Sunday. Seven days. One week.
星期一到星期日、七天、一週
I'm sure he had many other women.
他肯定有過一大堆女人
To spice up his performance, or whatever.
從女人身上獲取靈感
He was an actor, right?
他以前是演員吧？
I heard from Mom. Why is it that after you got famous,
我聽媽媽說了 你為什麼要在聲名大噪
that you quit the industry at the peak of your stardom?
人氣當紅時退出演藝圈
Not the industry, but I quit acting.
與其說演藝圈，應該說演員生涯吧
Right.
是的
It got boring after I got famous.
出名後生活開始變得很無趣
What?
什麼？
I heard a gong sound going, "Ring! It's over!"
有種結束鐘聲響起的感覺
I got caught up in the numbers of sales and popularity.
只在乎作品是不是有大賣 眼裡只有數字
I was fully booked, from morning to night.
從早到晚塞滿行程
My manager would circle around me,
經紀人像環繞行星的衛星般圍繞著我
I would buy a big house.
買了大房子
But I couldn't move from there.
變得無法動彈
Even the lines
到最後
written in the script felt like I was being trapped.
就連劇本上的台詞都令我感到束縛
Why do I have to say something I don't agree with?
我為什麼非得講出言不由衷的話？
Am I a robot?
我是機器人嗎？
Why did you want to become an actor, then?
那你還選擇當演員？
-Sorry. -No.
-對不起 -不
You're exactly right.
你說的沒錯
Sora, are you a college student?
你是大學生嗎？
Yes. I'm still in school.
是的，我還是大學生
You have a long future ahead.
你的人生才正要開始
Here.
給你
Let's go fishing for our dinner.
我們去釣晚餐要吃的魚吧
If we're lucky, we can get a largescale blackfish.
運氣好的話，能釣到黑毛
-Let's get something to eat. -Sure.
-去吃東西吧 -愛梨想吃甜食
-Hi. -Something sweet?
不好意思
Hey, nose hair.
哇，鼻毛男
How long will you call me that?
現在還在提這件事啊？
ODAYA
（小田屋）
What do you want?
你決定了嗎？
Why are your friends here too?
他們為什麼要跟來？
They want the taiyaki here.
她說想吃這裡的鯛魚燒
What would you like?
要點餐嗎？
-One taiyaki and yakisoba, please. -Alright.
-我要鯛魚燒跟炒麵 -鯛魚燒跟炒麵
-I want to try the sanmayaki. -Oh, sounds good.
-我想要吃秋刀魚燒 -好的，沒問題
-Thank you. -Thanks.
-麻煩了 -好的
I'm not giving up on Sora.
那個，我不會放棄小空
-What? -Don't "What?" me.
-什麼？ -這什麼反應？
What would you like?
請問要點餐嗎？
-Sanmayaki.
-秋刀魚燒
You have the same tastes.
真有默契呢
-We don't.
-哪裡，並沒有
Alright.
好的
There's nothing between Sora and me.
是說，我跟小空之間什麼都沒有
But you call her Sora.
但你直接叫她“小空”
Hello?
喂
Sora, you're so popular!
小空，你好受歡迎
What?
什麼？
Right now Hikaru and Doctor Wataru are at Odaya,
現在阿光跟涉師傅人在小田屋
and they're fighting over you!
正在爭奪你呢
No way.
怎麼可能？
This makes no sense.
再說了，你跑來跟我下戰帖
-You declaring war on me. -Why?
-好像不太對吧 -什麼？
Romance is about two people.
戀愛是兩個人的事
It happens with two people, in a closed room.
是兩個人在密室裡發生的事
There's no space for a third party.
第三者是無法介入的
You're on a different level than me.
你好像等級很高
If you like her, you should just tell her.
既然你喜歡她，那就直接告訴她啊
I see.
這樣啊
You know,
抱歉
I'm not really experienced with these type of things.
說來慚愧，我不太習慣談戀愛
I've been treating old people as a chiropractor, and now I'm 25.
我一直都在推拿館照顧爺爺奶奶
Sorry. I just happened to overhear.
先生，我剛才聽你說
This guy has nothing to do with Sora Minase.
他跟水無瀨空沒有任何關係
They haven't even held hands.
連手都沒牽過
I've held hands.
我跟她牽過手
You're winning! By a long shot!
你贏了，壓倒性勝利
So have confidence.
你不用擔心
Was that your friend calling?
是你朋友嗎？
It seems I'm popular with the boys now.
我好像很搶手
What?
什麼？
Never mind.
沒事
It's because you're pretty.
因為你很可愛啊
But I'm an otaku.
我是宅女喔
It doesn't matter. If you're pretty, you're pretty.
不管是不是宅女，可愛就是可愛
What?
什麼？
You got all the girls, right?
一之瀨先生，你以前很受歡迎吧？
No, that's not true.
沒有啦，我一點也不受歡迎
You toyed with my birth mother and my foster mother.
因為我的生母跟養母都被你玩弄了
That's a bit harsh.
玩弄嗎？你講話真毒啊
Oh? Is it pulling?
上鉤了嗎？
You're right!
真的呢
It's pulling… Huh?
真的…奇怪？
Is this your first time fishing?
你是第一次釣魚嗎？
Yes!
是的
A live fish? A live fish is coming, right?
是生魚吧？會釣到生魚吧？
-You're reeling it the wrong way. -What?
-捲線器轉反了 -什麼？
Reel it in harder.
-你要轉緊 -是這邊啊
-Oh, this way? -Yes, keep reeling.
再轉緊一點
-Yes! -Just like that.
-是 -就是這樣
-Wow! -Nice!
-哇！ -很好
I came to ask if you have Wi-Fi.
我去問了有沒有WiFi
Wi-Fi?
WiFi？
The internet!
就是網路啊
Without the internet, I can't send my manuscript.
若連不上網路 我沒辦法把稿子寄出去
What's the internet?
什麼是網路？
Mom, he's clueless.
媽媽，他不行啦
He lives like a caveman.
他的生活簡直是原始人
He fishes for his food.
還去海邊釣魚
I was joking.
我開玩笑的
ENTER THE SECURITY CODE
（輸入網路安全金鑰）
Here you are.
好了
Wow, fish!
哇！魚…
It's fresh.
真有活力啊
Wow.
你真厲害
You're a hard worker.
你的工作真辛苦
Sure.
是啊
But I just have to type it out and send it.
不過現在只要 把寫好的稿子寄出就行了
Take your time.
你慢慢用
I'm going to prepare dinner now.
我現在去準備晚餐
What, dinner?
咦？晚餐？
I'll pitch a tent and sleep outside.
我會搭帳篷睡在外面
You two can sleep here.
你們就睡這裡吧
We're sleeping here?
咦？我們要過夜嗎？
It's a tiny world.
你的世界很小呢
The ten centimeter radius
只有十根手指頭的範圍
of your ten fingers.
半徑10公分
I collect driftwood from around the world here.
而我則是撿拾全世界的漂流木
They all have different shapes,
每一個的形狀都不同
with different histories.
每一個都有自己的歷史
Histories that floated here.
隨著海浪漂流的歷史
True, Mom's work is nothing like picking up driftwood.
媽媽的工作跟撿漂流木的確差很多
It's a small world.
沒有世界規模，很小
It's just Mom's small head that is involved.
只存在媽媽小小的頭腦裡
There might not be much in her brain.
可能也沒多少腦漿
Hey!
喂
But the world she creates from there is really big.
但是從那裡創作出來的世界 非常的龐大
It's infinite. It makes many people happy.
無限大，可以帶給很多人幸福
She grew up to be a good girl.
你養育了一個好女兒
MIDSUMMER SKIES ARE DREAMS - AOI MINASE
（《仲夏藍天之夢》）
Oh, it's nice. The intro's catchy.
喔
She got the inspiration from Ibuse's Salamander.
好像是想模仿井伏鱒二的《山椒魚》
"Mom died two weeks ago.
“媽媽死了，就在兩個星期前
I haven't been able to cry for two weeks."
我到現在仍然一滴淚也沒流”
What does this mean?
這段嗎？
I don't know either.
我也不懂
A writer's head is unique,
作家的腦袋很獨特
so it must connect with the story later on.
也許有特別的劇情安排吧
But now, we can take this to Lemon Page and have them print her name really big.
在《Lemon Page》上 大大地印出水無瀨碧的名字吧
Yes, sir.
那太好了
Looks like it's the return of Aoi Minase.
水無瀨碧也終於復活了
Alright! Let's go out for drinks!
好，今天去喝酒激勵一下士氣吧
Come on. Join us once in a while, Soseki!
漱石小弟，偶爾也配合一下吧
Hey, you actually have a pretty cute face!
仔細看看你真的長得不錯
You remind me of someone.
每次看到你，我就會想起那個人
There was this kid who could never finish his milk and had to stay at the table.
以前班上不敢喝牛奶 總是剩下來的同學
You look like him.
真的很像他
I hope Takeshi's doing alright.
不知道阿武過得如何
I'm sorry. I need to go somewhere today.
對不起，我還有事
You're just going to go home and watch Hulu, right?
你能有什麼事？ 反正也只是回家看Hulu吧
Why Hulu?
為什麼一口咬定是Hulu？
That's behind the scenes stuff, okay?
大人間的事啦，識相一點
-It's fine. Hey, Tayama! -Yes?
-算了，田山 -是
-Let's go drink. -Yes, sir!
-去喝酒了 -好的
-Hello, welcome! -Welcome.
-歡迎光臨 -歡迎
Are you still open?
還可以點餐嗎？
Yes, come in.
當然，請坐
Here you are.
久等了
Are you back from Aoi's place?
你剛才去找小碧嗎？
Oh, no.
不是
Right. She's at Ouse Island now.
對喔，她現在人在逢瀨島
I just happened to be in the area.
我正好來到附近
Why?
為什麼？
There are a lot of good restaurants nearby.
這一帶很多店 為何偏偏選我們這裡？
-I hope I didn't inconvenience you. -Oh, no.
給你添麻煩了嗎？
Customers are everything.
客人就是神啊
Or did you come to see your ex? Sally?
還是你來看以前的女友沙沙？
Sally went with Shunichiro,
她跟俊一郎
my father, to the Suzuran Hot Springs. It's nearby.
就是我老爸 他們一起去隔壁的鈴蘭溫泉了
I think they're getting dinner and drinks after.
之後應該會去哪裡吃飯喝酒吧
They're so in love.
真是恩愛
Did I hurt you? Did I pick at old wounds?
我是不是在你的傷口上撒鹽了？
-I'm sorry! -No, it's fine.
-對不起 -啊，不會…
I'm over Sally.
我已經不在意她的事了
-As long as she's happy. -No, I'm sorry.
-只要她幸福就好 -不，對不起
That was so rude of me.
我這人真的很不貼心
Aoi always says I am the most insensitive guy ever.
小碧常說我把貼心忘在老媽肚子裡了
Let me let you eat. Go ahead.
我坐這裡會干擾你用餐吧
Oh, no.
不會
Please join me.
你不介意的話
Really?
可以嗎？
You know, maybe the reason I came here is because
我之所以選擇來這裡
I wanted to talk to someone I know.
也許是想來找認識的人
I don't have any other place to go.
我沒有常去的店
Really?
是嗎？
Being alone can be rough during the winter.
冬天一個人真的很難熬
-Kenta, can you get me a cup? -Yes, sir!
-健太 -是
-Marshmallows? -Yeah.
-棉花糖？ -對啊…
You know how you roast them while camping?
露營不是常常烤棉花糖嗎？
And you pitched a tent?
是喔，你們搭了帳篷啊
We also ate the fish we caught.
他烤了釣到的魚當晚餐
And we also ate napa cabbage and pork hot pot.
還有白菜加豬肉的火鍋
Ichinose bought those ingredients.
這是他去買食材回來煮的
Also, we caught some clams and grilled them
還有啊，我們還撈到蛤蜊
with soy sauce and butter too!
配醬油跟奶油一起烤來吃
That sounds good.
好像很好吃
We're having tea soon.
現在吃飽正準備喝茶
The stars are pretty.
星星好美喔
And how is Fuga Ichinose?
一之瀨風雅是什麼樣的人？
He's a strange man.
感覺有點神奇
You punch him yet?
你有賞他一拳嗎？
How do I put it…?
該怎麼說呢？
He's on a different plane of existence.
好像不在同一個次元裡
Like a whale shark at the aquarium.
就像海生館裡的豆腐鯊
Hey,
是說你為什麼要打給我？
Shouldn't you be calling your boyfriend?
通常這種時候應該會找男友吧
Should I not call you?
你覺得困擾嗎？
No, it's fine with me, but…
也…也不是啦，我並不覺得困擾
I wasn't doing anything anyway. So it's fine.
反正我很閒，是無所謂啦
I was told to keep this a secret from you,
他叫我不要說 所以我應該不能告訴你
but I saw Doctor Wataru today.
我今天遇到涉師傅了
You're telling me.
你已經說了
I'm keeping some details a secret.
這樣已經很客氣了
I ran into him by chance at Odaya.
我們碰巧在小田屋碰到
-I see. -You guys held hands, right?
-是 -你們牽手了吧？
If you held hands, that means you're dating.
牽手就算是戀人了
That's so innocent. It's unlike you.
什麼？這麼純情真不像你
You like Doctor Wataru, right? So call him.
你喜歡涉師傅吧？去打給他吧
-What? -Bye.
-什麼？ -再見
Hey, wait…
喂…
What's with him?
什麼意思啊？
I'm so immature!
我真是幼稚
You can get hot water from here.
這邊有熱水
You seem to be getting along well.
相處得很融洽嘛
With Sora.
你跟小空
She's a city girl,
她是都市小孩
so she's never gone fishing.
從來沒有釣過魚
Ichinose! The campfire's about to go out.
一之瀨先生，營火好像快熄滅了
Right. Coming.
知道了
-Check it out. -Yes?
-你看那個 -是
It's driftwood that Fuga Ichinose found.
那個一之瀨風雅撿的漂流木
It feels wrong somehow.
討厭，感覺很討厭
What do you mean?
很討厭嗎？
It's shady to sell driftwood that you found, right?
太可疑了，居然在撿漂流木來賣
It feels more honest to make and sell taiyaki.
做鯛魚燒生意感覺比較誠實
Right? We use flour.
就是啊，那是麵粉
Flour and bean paste. At least you know where it comes from.
麵粉跟紅豆餡，大家都知道
She's too naive, don't you think?
那傢伙人太好了啦
Ms. Aoi is?
小碧老師嗎？
She got dumped by a guy, and raised his girl's kid.
被男人拋棄，收養別人的小孩
I mean it's Sora, but she raised her.
把小空拉拔長大
Now, Sora wants to meet her dad and Aoi's taking her.
現在女兒說想見爸爸就帶她去
Maybe Ms. Aoi wanted to see Ichinose too.
小碧老師應該也想見他吧
What do you mean?
什麼？
Because she said it was a great love.
她說自己很愛他啊
I fell in love.
我談了一場戀愛
It was different from any love I've experienced.
跟以往的戀情截然不同
It was an all-consuming love, like I was struck by lightning.
彷彿受到雷擊一般，撼動心弦的戀愛
But he forgot about her.
雖然對方好像不記得了
What?
什麼？
He didn't remember?
對方忘了？
Yes. She told me on the phone.
是的，她在電話裡說的
You look happy.
你好像很開心
She's like that.
-那傢伙就像偶像一樣 -什麼？
When she was in her early twenties, she was always smart and pretty.
剛過二十歲就紅了
She was likable too. Not snobby or anything.
個性很好，也不會驕傲自大
-Right. -She went to a good high school.
-是 -上了好高中
To a good college.
上了好大學
And she wrote a novel and debuted as an author.
一動筆寫小說就出道了
Yes.
是
She didn't have to work her way up.
沒吃過什麼苦
Just like an idol
就跟在原宿被看中的偶像一樣
-We didn't do that! -But now she can't climb down.
-沒有拆台啦 -但她下不了台啊
And she's forced to wear ballerina shoes.
變成不自覺中被迫穿上芭蕾舞鞋
She's a ballerina that has to dance until she dies.
必須持續跳舞到死的舞伶
She didn't need to be that great.
她不必變成那種大人物
She should've married me and made taiyaki with me at Odaya.
嫁給我一起在小田屋 烤鯛魚燒不就好了嗎？
Do you love her?
你現在還是喜歡小碧老師嗎？
You do love her.
看來我說中了
You never get bored of
無論看多久
looking at this, right?
都不會看膩吧？
Everyone's faces are pretty.
大家的表情都好美…
Don't you think?
呢
You're right.
是啊
Soseki? Soseki, wake up.
漱石，起床了
Just let him sleep. He'll go home tomorrow morning.
沒關係，讓他睡吧 明天早上再走就好了
He can't drink, you know.
誰叫他不會喝硬要喝
I can't get away
我無法放下
From the phone
我手中的電話
I know I can't
我知道我無法
Hear your voice ever again
再次聽到你的聲音了
Sora.
小空
I thought you were wrong.
我原以為你是錯的
What?
什麼？
Imagine.
你想像一下
Reach your hand out in the darkness.
試著在黑暗中伸出手
Wait.
等一下
You're being weird.
你怪怪的
-Where are you right now, Sally? -At Odaya.
-沙沙，你在哪裡？ -小田屋
Soseki can't drink, but he did, and now he's asleep.
因為漱石不會喝酒還硬要喝 現在睡著了
He doesn't wake up once he goes to sleep.
他只要睡著就不容易醒了
He smells nostalgic.
他身上
Like the man I knew.
有前男友那種令人懷念的味道
What are you doing, Sally?
沙沙，你在幹嘛？
I'm comparing them.
我在比較
How it feels to be held by Shunichiro
比較俊一郎的胸膛
and Soseki.
跟漱石的胸膛
In whose arms do I feel more safe?
哪一邊會讓我更安心
In whose arms do I belong?
哪一邊才是我的歸處
Why are you comparing them now?
為什麼現在還要比較？
I thought you'd decided.
你不是決定了嗎？
There's no such thing as time with love.
戀愛沒有時限
When it goes back, it goes back.
該回去時就會回去
Time jumps
輕易就能跨越時間
I don't really get it, but…
雖然我聽不懂
That's deep.
但你好厲害
You're a pro at this.
真是專家
Being in the arms of an ex is
前男友的胸膛
different from love.
跟戀愛不同
It's like a bird
就像是一隻鳥
resting in an old nest.
停在老巢穴稍作休息
So it's Shunichiro, isn't it?
你已經選了俊一郎吧？
But my heart fluttered a bit.
有點心跳加速
Because Shunichiro's upstairs.
因為俊一郎就在二樓
Be careful with the risky games.
大人的遊戲要適可而止喔
Sora.
小空
Reach out in the darkness.
你試著在黑暗中伸出手看看
Your hand touches someone's shoulder,
你的手碰到誰的肩膀會感到安心？
That's the person
他就是你最需要的人喔
Is that what love is?
戀愛就是這樣嗎？
It's my opinion.
你就把我的意見
Just one of the theories out there.
當作一份考察研究去試試吧
Roger that.
收到
Sally.
沙沙
I hope you find happiness.
你要幸福喔
You too.
你也是
I liked how you were left-handed.
我很喜歡你的左撇子
Don't change it.
別改回來喔
It's too late for that.
已經改不回來了
That man is my dad.
他就是我的爸爸
My father.
我的父親
Can't sleep?
睡不著嗎？
No.
對
You want a drink?
要喝一杯嗎？
It's good.
好好喝
Is it? I'm glad.
是嗎？那就好
This shochu
這瓶
was made on this island.
是這座島上的燒酌
What do you usually drink, Sora?
你平常都喝什麼酒？
I don't really drink.
我不太喝酒
Just some limoncello.
只會喝一點Limoncello
What is that?
那是什麼？
It's a lemon alcohol.
就是檸檬酒
It's good.
很好喝
It's probably not for me.
我應該不會喜歡
I'm not good with sweets.
我不愛吃甜
How do you know it's sweet?
你怎麼知道是甜的？
Lemoncello sounds like a sweet drink.
檸夢酒聽起來就很甜
It's limoncello, not lemon.
是“檬”，“檸檬酒”
Are you cold?
你不會冷嗎？
No.
不會
It feels nice outside.
外面很舒服
Can I hear the rest of your story?
那個，可以繼續之前的話題嗎？
What was it?
什麼話題？
So,
你在當紅時放棄當演員
and after that…
後來呢？
Driftwood?
撿漂流木嗎？
No.
不是的
Let's see.
這個嘛
I earned many things from becoming famous,
我出名後得到很多東西
so I decided to get rid of many things.
所以想要試著捨棄各種東西
I got rid of my money.
我捨棄了錢
I donated it all.
拿去捐贈了
I got rid of my house.
也捨棄了房子
I got rid of everything.
全都捨棄了
But I pick up driftwood.
不過卻會撿拾漂流木
Just kidding.
騙你的
I only started picking up driftwood about ten years ago.
我是十年前才開始撿漂流木的
I did many things during that time.
在那之前我做過很多事
Many things?
很多事？
Yes.
是的
I opened a lodge in a tropical island.
我曾去南方小島的民宿工作
I sang songs.
或是去唱歌
-Songs? -Yes.
-唱歌？ -是啊
On the streets.
在路邊
Like a street musician.
像街頭藝人一樣
I tried many things,
做過各種工作
and went to many places.
去過各種地方
Can you live doing that?
這樣能過活嗎？
Sora.
小空
It's possible to live without money.
人沒有錢也能活下去喔
As long as there are people.
只要有人就夠了
-People? -Yes.
-人？ -是的
People who help you.
幫助自己的人
People you want to help.
自己想幫助的人
A give-and-take relationship.
相輔相成
I traveled to many places
在各地旅遊
and met many people.
認識各式各樣的人
I somehow
勉強能夠糊口
I woke up, and worked.
早上起床工作
When night came,
到了晚上
I ate a little bit of good food, and slept.
就吃點好吃的東西，入睡
You didn't want to do something?
你沒有什麼目標嗎？
Like a dream, maybe?
夢想之類的
My dream was
我的夢想
to be an actor.
曾經是當演員
My dream ended when I was 33.
這個夢想在我33歲時結束了
Since it came true.
因為實現了
And,
接著
I felt trapped, so…
我開始感到束縛
I got rid of my house.
我捨棄了家
And,
然後
I traveled to many different places.
到各地去流浪
You can live anywhere.
到哪裡都能住
I made the whole world my home.
我以四海為家
The whole world was your home?
以四海為家？
Yes.
是的
Like a migratory bird.
好像候鳥
Migratory birds travel the distance of half the Earth
候鳥靠著小小的身體
in a single year, with their small bodies.
一年能飛越半個地球的距離
The whole world is their home.
世界就是候鳥的家
That's nice.
真棒
What's going on?
為什麼？
Do they get along because they're related?
有血緣所以個性也很合嗎？
Shoot.
糟糕，我這樣會離不開孩子的
I'm sleeping.
睡吧
It's late!
夜深了
Do you know this song?
你知道這首曲子嗎？
No.
不知道
It's called "Will You Dance?"
曲名叫《與我共舞好嗎？》
It's nice.
好棒的曲子
Do you want to dance?
要跳舞嗎？
-What? -Let's dance.
-什麼？ -來跳舞吧
No, no. I can't.
不行，我不會跳
I've never danced in my life.
我打從出生就沒跳過舞
Then,
那就跟我跳人生的第一支舞吧
No, I can't.
我不行啦
What?
什麼？
Really?
真的假的？
The stars are pretty, huh?
星星很美嗎？
How nice.
真羨慕
What are you drawing?
你在畫什麼？
Mom.
媽媽
What?
什麼？
I'm so happy!
媽媽好高興
Where's Mr. Elephant?
大象，大象在哪裡？
Today's egg is pretty good.
今天的不錯吃
Seriously?
真的嗎？
-It's good! -Yeah!
-好好吃 -嗯
-Mom, hurry up! -I'm sorry!
-媽媽，快點啦 -對不起…
Alright.
糟糕，相機
SCHOOL ENTRANCE CEREMONY
（入學典禮）
Princess! I've brought a mountain of treasure
公主殿下
to obtain Sora.
如山的寶藏
Tiffany, Harry Winston, Bulgari!
Tiffany、LV、寶佳麗
I brought clothes, bags, and shoes.
我願獻上衣服、包包、鞋子
You can dress up how you please
讓公主如莉卡娃娃般
anytime you want, like a Barbie doll.
無論何時都能隨心所欲地打扮
Prada, Gucci, Margiela!
Prada Gucci、Margiela
Saint Laurent, Stella, Celine, Bottega!
聖羅蘭、Stella Celine、Bottega
I have some registration documents.
我願獻上土地登記書
Hawaii, New Zealand, Gold Coast, and Switzerland.
夏威夷、紐西蘭、黃金海岸
All vacation homes.
以及瑞士的別墅
I'll also give you an ancient castle in Europe.
還能附贈一座歐洲的古城
Princess! I have a signed copy of Happy Kanako.
公主，我願獻上 《加奈子的幸福殺手生活》簽名版
HAPPY KANAKO
（《加奈子的幸福殺手生活》）
And a treasure box,
以及這個寶箱
containing early sketches for Chainsaw Man.
裡面有《鏈鋸人》設定集
Limited figures, sold out at Comiket.
同人誌展售會當場秒殺的限定公仔
A complete set of Edens Zero, all fully painted.
《伊甸星原》的 全彩已塗裝珍藏版公仔
Finally,
最後最後
a limited illustrated Band-Aid of Cells at Work! only in Village Vanguard.
Village Vanguard 聯名限定的《工作細胞》OK繃也有
Your favorite character, White Blood Cell, is in there as well.
公主殿下最愛的白血球 當然也包含在內
No, Sora!
小空，不行
Real estate. Always go for real estate!
不動產…再怎麼樣都要選不動產
I have
我
a complete set of
願意獻上牛奶紫羅蘭
all flavors of Milba, also known as Milk and Violet.
牛奶紫羅蘭的全部口味
All flavors from the past and future.
從過去到未來即將推出的口味
This is called
這個
Sexual Violet.
是性感紫羅蘭口味
What does it taste like?
那是什麼味道？
No, I have to
我不收
return to the moon.
因為我必須回到月亮
I cannot accept anyone's proposal.
無論是哪位的求婚 都請恕我無法接受
You're going to the moon?
你要回月亮去嗎？
You took me in when you found me in a glowing bamboo
我本來就只是從樹海發亮的竹子裡
in the forest and raised me.
被你撿回來的孩子
I didn't do that.
沒有…
That was a lie.
那是謊話啊
No need for that. Step away.
別在意，請遠離我
You mean, "Come closer!"
通常應該要叫我靠近吧？
Bye, Mom!
再見，媽媽
I thought Princess Kaguya took an ox cart home.
輝夜姬不是搭牛車回去的嗎？
Are we suddenly in Arabian Nights?
為什麼只有這段變成 《一千零一夜》？
Thank you for everything.
謝謝你的照顧
Hey, wait!
等一下
Just a dream?
是夢啊
Of course
我想也是
Mom, I decided to travel with Fuga.
媽媽，我要暫時出去旅行
He took her.
被搶走了
WE'LL SHOW YOU BEHIND THE SCENES OF DATE MY DAUGHTER!
（《我家女兒交不到男朋友！》 幕後直擊）
Mom! Are you okay?
媽媽…沒事吧？
Okay.
好
REHEARSAL
（彩排）
Can I try? Will it mess up your hair?
我可以試試嗎？看會不會變亂
ASSISTANT DIRECTOR
（副導）
You'll treasure this memory forever!
最棒的回憶
-Aoi Minase. -What?
-水無瀨碧小姐 -什麼？
But he's fun to be with.
不過他有一點有趣
So that's Fuga Ichinose, huh?
他就是一之瀨風雅呀
It's an honor
榮升到散英社紐約分公司了
What is it?
幹嘛？
I'll smell your scent.
聞光的味道
You chased us all the way here.
你特地追到這裡來
What do you want?
到底想做什麼？